<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' ?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % BOOK_ENTITIES SYSTEM "Users_Guide.ent">
%BOOK_ENTITIES;
]>

<chapter id="Overview">

<title>CREAM Functional Description</title>

<para>
The CREAM (Computing Resource Execution And Management) Service is a simple, lightweight service that implements all the 
operations at the Computing Element (CE) level; its well-defined WebService-based interface and its implementation as an 
extension of the Java-Axis servlet (running inside the Apache Tomcat container) provide interoperability with clients 
written in any programming language and running on any computer platform.
</para>

<para>
The CREAM interface is well-defined using the Web Service Description Language (WSDL); anyone can generate his/her CREAM 
client by simply filling in the stub code generated by WSDL parser (gSOAP for C/C++, Axis for Java, Perl module for perl).
</para>

<para>
CREAM functionality:
<itemizedlist>
    <listitem><para>
    Job Submission
    <itemizedlist>
        <listitem><para>Possibility of direct staging of input sandbox files</para></listitem>
        <listitem><para>gLite JDL compliance (with CREAM-specific extensions)</para></listitem>
        <listitem><para>Support for batch and parallel jobs</para></listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    </para></listitem>
    <listitem><para>Manual and automatic proxy delegation</para></listitem>
    <listitem><para>Job Cancellation</para></listitem>
    <listitem><para>
    Job Info with configurable level of verbosity and filtering based on submission time and/or job status
    </para></listitem>
    <listitem><para>Job List</para></listitem>
    <listitem><para>Job Suspension and Resume</para></listitem>
    <listitem><para>Job output retrieval</para></listitem>
    <listitem><para>Job Purge for terminated jobs</para></listitem>
    <listitem><para>Possibility (for admin) to disable new submissions</para></listitem>
    <listitem><para>
    Self limiting CREAM behavior: CREAM is able to protect itself if the load, memory usage, etc. is too high. 
    This happens disabling new job submissions, while the other commands are still allowed
    </para></listitem>
    <listitem><para>ARGUS or gJAF based authorization</para></listitem>
    <listitem><para>Possibility to forward requirements to the batch system</para></listitem>
    <listitem><para>Integration with APEL accounting systems</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</para>

<para>
CREAM can be used
<itemizedlist>
    <listitem><para>
    by the Workload Management System (WMS), via the ICE (Interface to CREAM Environment) service
    </para></listitem>
    <listitem><para>
    by a generic client, e.g. an end-user willing to directly submit jobs to a CREAM CE.
    A C++ command line interface (CLI) is available
    </para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</para>
</chapter>
